Guide to the Lee Anderson Papers and Yale Series of Recorded Poets Sound Recordings
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Lee Anderson papers and Yale Series of Recorded Poets sound recordings
1951-1968
YCAL MSS 402
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
19.42
(23 boxes)
The Lee Anderson Papers and Yale Series of Recorded Poets Sound Recordings document the work of poet and editor Lee Anderson with the Yale Series of Recorded Poets. The bulk of the sound recordings consist of poetry readings by various poets and a small number contain poets' lectures on poetry. The papers consist of writings, correspondence, contracts, lists, procedural documentation, and printed material relating to the series production and publication.
Anderson, Lee, 1896-1972
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Lee Anderson, September 1974 and Washington University, 1980.
Custodial History
All sound recordings in this collection are duplicates of sound recordings held by the Yale Collection of Historical Sound Recordings (HSR). As Lee Anderson made sound recordings for the Yale Series of Recorded Poets in the 1950s and 1960s, he sent the original tapes to HSR for their collection. Anderson's 1974 gift to the Beinecke Library originally included 696 sound recordings. These recordings were sent to HSR for comparison of the material held by HSR. HSR retained the originals, to complete their collection of original recordings, and duplicates were returned to the Beinecke Library. Those returned duplicates comprise this collection.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Boxes 1-17: Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Associated Materials
Original sound recordings are held at Yale Collection of Historical Sound Recordings. Please see Provenance note for more information.
Selections of sound recordings have been digitized and are available through PennSound at http://writing.upenn.edu/pennsound.
Lee Anderson
Lee Anderson was born in Saxton, Pennsylvania and attended the University of Pittsburgh in 1896. He served in the U.S. Navy during World War I and spent several years as a self-employed printer and farmer in western Pennsylvania. In 1942, he published his collection of poetry, Prevailing Winds. Anderson became interested in poetry readings and the oral aspects of poetry and began to record contemporary poets reading their work onto audiotape. At first, Anderson kept the recordings for his personal collection but soon he was asked by the Library of Congress to record and submit recorded poetry readings to the library. He submitted approximately 100 tapes to the library.
In 1955, Yale University acquired Anderson's complete collection of more than 500 tapes of contemporary British and American poets reading from their work, including duplicates of recordings donated to the Library of Congress. In addition, Yale hired Anderson as a Research Associate. While at Yale, he helped produce the Yale Series of Recorded Poets, a collection of LP records of poets reading their work which was derived largely from Anderson's tape collection. Anderson made additional recordings of poets reading while he was at Yale. In addition to producing recordings, Anderson edited several books in his lifetime.
After leaving Yale, Anderson taught at several institutions and continued to write and lecture. He continued recording but primarily recorded his work. In the late 1960's Anderson became ill. He died in Florida in 1972.
Scope and Contents
The Lee Anderson Papers and Yale Series of Recorded Poets Sound Recordings document the work of poet and editor Lee Anderson in recording contemporary poets reading from their work and later producing the Yale Series of Recorded Poets. The bulk of the sound recordings consist of poetry readings by various poets and a small number of poets' lectures on poetry. The papers consist of writings, correspondence, contracts, lists, procedural documentation, and printed material relating to the series production and publication. Included among the papers is Lee Anderson's notebook draft of "Memoirs," containing observations of poets reading for the Yale Series of Record Poets. The sound recordings and papers span the years 1951 to 1968.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Sound Recordings, 1951-1968. II. Papers, 1951-1968.
Poets -- 20th Century; British poetry -- 20th Century; American poetry -- 20th Century; Sound recordings; Anderson, Lee, 1896-1972
- Sound Recordings, 1951-1968; Series I; 17; (17 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by poet's name.
  Scope and Contents
  All sound recordings are 7 inch 1/4" reel-to-reel tape formats unless otherwise noted. Numbers in brackets represent number of reels.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Boxes 1-17: Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - Adams, Léonie [3], 1951 November 9 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
    Existence and Location of Copies
    Reference copy available for all reels. Stored in Box 22.
  - Aiken, Conrad [12], 1966 October 6 (Box 1, Folder 2-8)
  - Alfred, William [2], 1959 September 15 (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
  - Anderson, Lee [2], 1960 (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
  - Auden, W. H. [4], 1959 March 18; 1959 March 19 (Box 1, Folder 10-12)
  - Basler, Roy [4], 1955 February 11; 1955 December 11; 1956 July 22; 1959 May 3 (Box 1, Folder 12-14)
  - Beach, Joseph [1], 1957 March 25 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Beecham, Audrey [3], 1960 June 9; 1960 June 10 (Box 1, Folder 15-16)
  - Beer, Patricia [3], 1960 June 17 (Box 1, Folder 16-17)
  - Belitt, Ben [2], 1958 April 20 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Bennett, Joe [1], [undated] (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Berryman, John [3], 1951 April 30 (Box 2, Folder 19-20)
  - Betjeman, John [6], 1960 May 18; 1960 June 18; 1968 July (Box 2, Folder 21-23)
  - Blackburn, Thomas [2], 1960 June 6; 1960 June 7 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Blackmur, R.P. [8], 1959 December (Box 2, Folder 25-28)
  - Bogan, Louise [5], 1967 May 4 (Box 2, Folder 29-31)
  - Bogardus, Edgar [1], 1957 March 2 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Booth, Phillip [2], 1958 April 13 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Bridson, Geoffrey [2], 1960 June 9 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Brinnin, John Malcolm [2], 1961 May 15; 1956 August 6 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Brown, Spencer [4], 1958 March 22 (Box 3, Folder 35-36)
  - Burford, William [1], 1951 March 24 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Burnshaw, Stanley [3], undated (Box 3, Folder 37-38)
  - Carrier, Constance [2], 1956 July 28 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Ciardi, John [5], 1959 November 5 (Box 3, Folder 40-42)
  - Coleman, Eliot [3], [undated] (Box 3, Folder 42-43)
  - Cunningham, J. V. [2], 1958 April 15 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Denney, Reuel [5], 1956 February 21 (Box 3, Folder 45-47)
  - Deutsch, Babette [9], 1951 May 22; 1951 November 5; 1959 October 2 (Box 3, Folder 47-51)
  - Dicksinson, Patrick [2], 1960 June 17 (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Duncan, Robert [3], 1952 (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Dyment, Clifford [4], 1960 April 24; 1960 April 25 (Box 4, Folder 53-55)
  - Eaton, Charles E. [4], 1958 November 51 (Box 4, Folder 55-57)
  - Eberhart, Richard [5], 1953; 1963 October 5 (Box 4, Folder 57-59)
  - Eliot, T.S. [2], 1967 June 3 (Box 4, Folder 60)
  - Elliot, George [2], 1959 November 5 (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - Empson, Williams [4], 1960 May 19 (Box 4, Folder 62-63)
  - Fitts, Dudley [8], 1958 April 16; 1959 November 14 (Box 4, Folder 64-67)
  - Fitts, Dudley [11], undated (Box 5, Folder 68-73)
  - Fitzgerald, Robert [2], 1957 April 12 (Box 5, Folder 73-74)
  - Frankenberg, Lloyd [3], 1951 November 4; 1951 November 5; 1951 November 14 (Box 5, Folder 74-75)
  - Frost, Frances [2], 1955 April 17 (Box 5, Folder 76)
  - Frost, Robert [6], 1961 May 19; 1966 November 21; undated (Box 5, Folder 77-79)
  - Fuller, Roy [3], 1960 April 27 (Box 5, Folder 80-81)
  - Gardner, Isabella [5], 1953 February 15; 1955 August; 1957 April 10 (Box 5, Folder 81-83)
  - Garrigue, Jean [6], 1951 November 10; 1960 March 8 (Box 6, Folder 84-86)
  - Geiger, Dan [3], 1958 September 23 (Box 6, Folder 87-88)
  - Gregory, Horace [1], 1951 November 9 (Box 6, Folder 88)
  - Hall, Donald [3], [undated] (Box 6, Folder 89-90)
  - Hall, Carol and James [2], 1955 October 24 (Box 6, Folder 90-91)
  - Hamburger, Michael [2], 1960 May 24 (Box 6, Folder 91-92)
  - Hartley, George [1], 1960 June 14 (Box 6, Folder 92)
  - Hecht, Anthony [6], 1959 December 9 (Box 6, Folder 93-95)
  - Hill, Lewis [1], 1952 February 24 (Box 6, Folder 96)
  - Hoffman, Daniel G. [4], 1955 April 24; 1960 March 12 (Box 6, Folder 96-98)
  - Hollander, John [3], 1959 March 10 (Box 6, Folder 98-99)
  - Hollander, John [3], 1959 March 10 (Box 7, Folder 100-101)
  - Holmes, John [3], 1951 May 15; 1956 August 1 (Box 7, Folder 101-102)
  - Honig, Edwin [3], 1959 June (Box 7, Folder 103-104)
  - Hopkins, G. M. (read by Cyril Cusack) [1], [undated] (Box 7, Folder 104)
  - Horan, Robert [1], 1952 March 24 (Box 7, Folder 105)
  - Hoskins, Katherine [3], 1958 April 12 (Box 7, Folder 105-106)
  - Howes, Barbara [9], 1951 February 2; 1958 April; 21; 1959 December 8 (Box 7, Folder 107-111)
  - Hughes, Ted [7], 1958 April 18; 1960 May 17 (Box 7, Folder 111-114)
  - Humphries, Rolfe [2], 1958 June 16 (Box 7, Folder 115)
  - Ingalls, Jeremy [1], 1951 May 15 (Box 7, Folder 116)
  - Jacobsen, Josephine [4], [undated] (Box 7, Folder 116)
  - Jacobsen, Josephine [4], [undated] (Box 8, Folder 117-118)
  - Jarrell, Randall [5], 1951 September 28; 1951 September 29; 1951 October 28; 1951 October 30 (Box 8, Folder 118-120)
  - Jones, David [2], 1960 May 22 (Box 8, Folder 121)
  - Joyce, James [1], [undated] (Box 8, Folder 122)
  - Kees, Weldon [1], 1952 March 28 (Box 8, Folder 122)
  - Kennedy, Gerta [1], 1959 September 16 (Box 8, Folder 123)
  - Kinnel, Galway [3], 1959 March 20 (Box 8, Folder 123-124)
  - Kizer, Carolyn [2], 1958 September 16 (Box 8, Folder 125)
  - Kunitz, Stanley [6], 1959 November 4 (Box 8, Folder 126-128)
  - Larkin, Philip [3], 1960 May 20 (Box 8, Folder 129-130)
  - Lee, Laurie [2], 1960 June 11 (Box 8, Folder 130-131)
  - Lehman, John [3], 1960 May 20 (Box 8, Folder 131-132)
  - Lehman, John [1], 1960 May 20 (Box 9, Folder 133)
  - Levertov, Denise [2], 1958 June 15 (Box 9, Folder 133-134)
  - Lewis, C. Day [9], 1960 May 16; 1960 June 3 (Box 9, Folder 134-138)
    Includes one 5" reel
  - Logan, John [2], 1951 April 16; 1957 April 12 (Box 9, Folder 139)
  - Logue, Christopher [2], 1960 June 6 (Box 9, Folder 140)
  - Lowell, Robert [8], 1959 September 12; 1959 September 13 (Box 9, Folder 141-144)
    Reference copy available for reels 3, 4, and 5. Stored in Box 22.
  - MacDiarmid, Hugh [4], 1960 June 10 (Box 9, Folder 145-146)
    - Translation of Rilke
    - Poetry
  - MacNeice, Louis [5], 1960 April 23 (Box 10, Folder 147-149)
  - Marshall, Lemore [4], 1958 March 16; 1958 March 17 (Box 10, Folder 149-151)
  - Mayhall-Granger, Jane [2], 1951 May 21; 1951 November 8 (Box 10, Folder 151-152)
  - Merrill, James [5], 1960 February 2 (Box 10, Folder 152-154)
  - Miles, Josephine [2], 1952;1958 (Box 10, Folder 155-156)
  - Miller, Mary Owings [4], [undated] (Box 10, Folder 156-158)
  - Moore, Marianne [3], 1951; undated (Box 10, Folder 158-159)
  - Moore, Merrill [4], 1953 May 9; 1953 May 10; 1953 May 11 (Box 10, Folder 160-161)
  - Moore, Richard [1], 1952 March 23 (Box 10, Folder 162)
    Reference copy available. Stored in Box 22.
  - Morse, Samuel French [2], 1956 July 31 (Box 10, Folder 162-163)
  - Moss, Howard [2], 1955 April 19 (Box 10, Folder 164)
  - Nemerov, Howard [4], 1958 April 19; 1958 April 20 (Box 11, Folder 165)
  - Nemerov, Howard [1] (Box 11, Folder 165-167)
  - Nims, John F. [1], 1957 April 11 (Box 11, Folder 168)
  - O'Connor, William Van [2], 1957 March 24 (Box 11, Folder 168-169)
  - Ostroff, Anthony [4], 1959 March 15 (Box 11, Folder 169-171)
  - Pitter, Ruth [5], 1960 April 26; 1958 June (Box 11, Folder 171-173)
  - Plath, Sylvia-Ted Hughes [2], 1958 April 18 (Box 11, Folder 174)
    Reference copy available for both reels. Stored in Box 22.
  - Plomer, William [3], 1960 May 26 (Box 11, Folder 175-176)
  - Pound, Ezra [2], 1966 November 26 (Box 11, Folder 176-177)
  - Prince, Frank Templeton [2], 1960 June 3 (Box 11, Folder 177-178)
  - Rago, Henry [1], [undated] (Box 11, Folder 178)
  - Raine, Kathleen [4], 1960 May 11; 1960 May 31 (Box 11, Folder 179-180)
  - Ransom, John Crowe [2], [undated] (Box 11, Folder 181)
  - Ransom, John Crowe [1], [undated] (Box 12, Folder 182)
  - Read, Sir Herbert [1], 1960 June 8 (Box 12, Folder 182)
  - Redgrove, Peter [2], 1960 May 28 (Box 12, Folder 183)
  - Rexroth, Kenneth [1], [undated] (Box 12, Folder 184)
  - Rich, Adrienne Cecile [1], 1958 May 14 (Box 12, Folder 184)
  - Ridler, Anne [2], 1960 May 19 (Box 12, Folder 185)
  - Rodgers, W.R. [1], 1960 June 13 (Box 12, Folder 186)
  - Rouse, Al [3], 1960 May 23 (Box 12, Folder 186-187)
  - Rukeyser, Muriel [4], 1959 March 21 (Box 12, Folder 188-189)
  - Scherill, James [3], 1958 September 21 (Box 12, Folder 190-191)
  - Scorill, E.J. [3], 1960 June 1 (Box 12, Folder 191-192)
  - Scott, Tom [4], [undated] (Box 12, Folder 193-194)
  - Scott, Winfield Townley [5], 1951 May 16; 1953 October 6; 1967 April 7 (Box 12, Folder 195-197)
  - Sexton, Anne [2], 1959 September 14 (Box 12, Folder 197-198)
  - Silkin, John [1], 1960 June 14 (Box 12, Folder 198)
  - Silkin, John [1], 1960 June 14 (Box 13, Folder 199)
  - Simpson, Louise [13], 1959 March 19; 1967 April 6 (Box 13, Folder 199-205)
  - Smith, William J. [7], 1951 July 2; 1951 July 4; 1951 July 7; 1958 April 21 (Box 13, Folder 206-209)
  - Spender, Stephen [5], 1955 April 25; 1960 May 2 (Box 13, Folder 209-211)
  - Stafford, William [2], 1958 September 18 (Box 13, Folder 212)
  - Stallman, Robert [1], 1955 April 28 (Box 13, Folder 213)
  - Starbuck, George [5], 1959 May 12; 1959 December 7 (Box 13, Folder 213-215)
  - Starbuck, George [4], 1960 January 24 (Box 14, Folder 216-217)
  - Swenson, May [3], 1958 March 15 (Box 14, Folder 218-219)
  - Tate, Allen [5], [1951]; 1959 September 13 (Box 14, Folder 219-221)
  - Thwaite, Anthony [3], 1960 June 27 (Box 14, Folder 222-223)
  - Tiller, Terrence [6], 1960 May 24 (Box 14, Folder 223-226)
  - Van Doren, Mark [4], 1951 May 20 (Box 14, Folder 226-228)
  - Van Duyn, Mona [2], 1957 March 16; 1957 March 17 (Box 14, Folder 228-229)
  - Wagner, David [2], 1958 September 17 (Box 14, Folder 229-230)
  - Warren, Robert Penn [5], undated (Box 14, Folder 230-232)
  - Warren, Robert Penn [3], undated (Box 15, Folder 233-234)
  - Watkins, Vernon [6], 1960 May 10; 1960 May 28 (Box 15, Folder 234-237)
  - Weiss, Theodore [19], 1959 February 9; 1960 March 9; 1967 April 10 (Box 15, Folder 237-246)
  - Wheelock, John Hall [6], 1955 October 18 (Box 15, Folder 247-249)
  - Wheelock, John Hall [4], 1960 February 26 (Box 16, Folder 250-251)
  - Wilbur, Richard [12], 1951 May 15; 1959 October 3 (Box 16, Folder 252-257)
  - Williams, Oscar [2], 1955 April 15 (Box 16, Folder 258)
  - Winakur, Maxine [3], 1959 September 17 (Box 16, Folder 259-260)
  - Winters, Yvon [11], 1964 June 24 (Box 16, Folder 260-265)
  - Yeats, W.B. [1], undated (Box 16, Folder 266)
  - Young, Reverend Andrew [1], 1960 June 2 (Box 16, Folder 266)
  - Unidentified tapes, undated; 6 (Box 17)
    Includes three 5" reels and one cassette
- Papers, 1951-1968; Series II; 1.5; (5 boxes)
  - Typescript and handwritten drafts of poems from various poets, 1951-1968, undated; 15 (Box 17)
    Arranged alphabetically by poet, A-R
  - Typescript and handwritten drafts of poems from various poets, 1951-1968, undated; 4 (Box 18)
    Arranged alphabetically by poet, S-Z
  - "Memoirs," three manuscript notebooks containing Anderson's observations of poets reading for the Yale Series of Recorded Poets, 1969; 3 (Box 18)
  - "Memoirs," one manuscript notebook containing Anderson's observations of poets reading for the Yale Series of Recorded Poets, 1969; 2 (Box 19)
    Includes clippings
  - Nags Head, galley proofs, 1960 (Box 23)
  - Correspondence, 1951-1968, undated
    - Anderson, Lee (Box 20)
    - Academy of American Poets (Box 20)
    - Arizona Quarterly (Box 20)
    - "A" miscellaneous (Box 20)
    - Brooks, Cleanth (Box 20)
    - "B" miscellaneous (Box 20)
    - Ciardi, John (Box 20)
    - Ellsworth, Jr., John S. (Box 20)
    - Epoch (Box 20)
    - Gallup, Donald (Box 20)
    - Garrigue, Jean (Box 20)
    - Green, Tom (Box 20)
    - Hartley, George (Box 20)
    - Hoellering, G.M. (Box 20)
    - "H" miscellaneous (Box 20)
    - Josephson, Louis (Box 20)
    - Kernan, Alvin B. (Box 20)
    - Kerr, Edith (Box 20)
    - Kone, Elliott H. (Box 20)
    - "L" miscellaneous (Box 20)
    - Mack, Maynard (Box 20)
    - MacLeish, Archibald (Box 20)
    - Martin, Jay (Box 20)
    - Martz, Louis (Box 20)
    - National Association of Educational Broadcasters (Box 20)
    - New Mexico Quarterly (Box 20)
    - Partisan Review (Box 20)
    - "R" miscellaneous (Box 20)
    - "S" miscellaneous (Box 20)
    - Viking Press (Box 20)
    - Waith, Eugene M. (Box 20)
    - "W" miscellaneous (Box 20)
    - Unidentified (Box 20)
    - "A-Z" miscellaneous, 28 (Box 23)
  - Agreements and contracts, 1959, undated; 2 (Box 20)
    Between Yale University and Lee Anderson, between Yale University and Poetry London-New York
  - Outline of procedures for editors of the Yale Poetry series, 1960 October 11 (Box 20)
  - Appointments with various poets, undated (Box 20)
  - Budget for broadcast of Yale Series of Recorded Poets over NAEB and other outlets, undated (Box 20)
  - Broadcast (Anderson/Kerr), undated (Box 20)
  - Index of sound recordings, undated (Box 20)
  - Miscellaneous papers of Lee Anderson, 1961, 1964 (Box 20)
  - Various lists, undated; 5 (Box 20)
    Includes lists for the Lee Anderson Collection of Recorded Poets and a list of poems selected for recording by Richard Eberhart, Robert Frost, and Edwin Honig
  - Proposal for the production of literature phonograph records by Yale University, undated (Box 20)
  - Editorial material from the Yale Series of Recorded Poets (Box 20)
    - Eberhert, R. Correspondence concerning his recorded poetry, 1959-1960 (Box 20)
    - Hollander, John. Correspondence, poetry drafts and printed material regarding recorded poetry, 1960-1961 (Box 20)
    - Scott, Winfield T. Correspondence concerning his recorded poetry; handwritten and typed drafts and page proofs of poetry, corrected, 1961 (Box 20)
    - Tate, Allan. Correspondence regarding his recorded poetry, undated (Box 20)
    - Waith, Eugene M. Yale Series of Recorded Poets page proofs, corrected, undated (Box 20)
    - Warnke, Frank J. Yale Series of Recorded Poets, Louis MacNeice typescript draft, corrected, undated (Box 20)
    - Warren, R.P. Correspondence concerning his recorded poetry; handwritten and typescript drafts; printed material; and page proof, corrected, 1960 (Box 20)
    - Memos, notes and clippings regarding the Yale Series of Recorded Poets Sound Recordings, 1957-1960; 2 (Box 20)
    - Printed material and pamphlets to accompany recordings, undated (Box 21)
  - List of Lee Anderson correspondents, photocopies, undated; 2 (Box 23)
- Reference Copies (Box 22)
  Available reference copies are noted in the listing above.